<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Notes | Jorge Israel Peña]]></title>
  <link href="http://blaenkdenum.com/categories/notes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blaenkdenum.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-22T20:41:40-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blaenkdenum.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jorge Israel Peña]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning ffmpeg]]></title>
    <link href="http://blaenkdenum.com/posts/learning-ffmpeg/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-17T17:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blaenkdenum.com/posts/learning-ffmpeg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been trying to understand <a href="http://www.ffmpeg.org/">ffmpeg</a> enough to use for decoding audio in a personal application I’m working on. Documentation and resources to learn it are a bit low and inconsistent or usually outdated. Here I try to maintain a list of resources and information I’ve learned about the library.</p>

<p>These notes will be updated as I learn more about ffmpeg.</p>

<h3 id="resources">Resources</h3>

<p>A problem I’ve encountered with ffmpeg is that many articles posted about it or open source found online is already outdated. Many modern applications like <a href="http://mpc-hc.org/">MPC-HC</a> and <a href="http://www.chromium.org/Home">Chromium</a> do seem to use the latest version of the APIs. I also quickly learned that most learning is done through looking at the examples in ffmpeg as well as the ffplay source.</p>

<ul>
  <li>the updated version of the <a href="http://dranger.com/ffmpeg/">ffmpeg tutorial</a> hosted <a href="https://github.com/chelyaev/ffmpeg-tutorial/blob/master/tutorial03.c#L114">here</a></li>
  <li>the <a href="https://github.com/FFmpeg/FFmpeg/blob/master/ffplay.c#L2133"><code>ffplay.c</code></a> source</li>
  <li>the ffmpeg <a href="https://github.com/FFmpeg/FFmpeg/tree/master/doc/examples">examples</a></li>
  <li>a <a href="http://www.gamedev.net/topic/624876-how-to-read-an-audio-file-with-ffmpeg-in-c/#entry4940299">post</a> on gamedev</li>
  <li>the <a href="https://github.com/mpc-hc/mpc-hc/blob/master/src/filters/transform/MpaDecFilter/FFAudioDecoder.cpp#L295">mpc-hc</a> source</li>
  <li>the <a href="http://src.chromium.org/svn/trunk/src/media/filters/audio_file_reader.cc">chromium source</a></li>
</ul>

<p>One particular thing about decoding audio is that it is generally decoded to a format that was used during the encoding process. This could be PCM Float Planar format for example, where each sample is a float and each channel is stored in a separate buffer. However, when you want to use the audio or play it through speakers, sometimes the format required can differ from the format decoded to. Fortunately ffmpeg has <a href="http://ffmpeg.org/libswresample.html">libswresample</a> which can make these conversions easy. There also exists an abstraction of this using <a href="http://ffmpeg.org/libavfilter.html">libavfilter</a>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>commit <a href="https://github.com/FFmpeg/FFmpeg/commit/e96175ad7b576ad57b83d399193ef10b2bb016ae"><code>e96175ad</code></a> that adds avfilter support to ffplay</li>
  <li>libswresample’s <a href="https://github.com/FFmpeg/FFmpeg/blob/master/doc/examples/resampling_audio.c">resampling audio</a> example</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Linux Programming Interface: Directories and Links]]></title>
    <link href="http://blaenkdenum.com/posts/the-linux-programming-interface-directories-and-links/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-06T17:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blaenkdenum.com/posts/the-linux-programming-interface-directories-and-links</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#directories">Directories</a></li>
  <li><a href="#hard-links">Hard Links</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#shared-pointers">Shared Pointers</a></li>
      <li><a href="#temporary-files">Temporary Files</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#symbolic-links">Symbolic Links</a></li>
  <li><a href="#directory-streams">Directory Streams</a></li>
  <li><a href="#working-directories">Working Directories</a></li>
  <li><a href="#root-directories">Root Directories</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Notes for chapter 18 concerning directories and links.</p>

<h2 id="directories">Directories</h2>

<p>Stored in the file system as a regular file except:</p>

<ol>
  <li>marked differently in its i-node entry</li>
  <li>data content is a table mapping filenames to i-node numbers</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="hard-links">Hard Links</h2>

<p>Hard links are also referred to simply as ‘links’. It is soft links which require additional qualification. Links can be created using the <code>ln</code> command which is often used to instead create soft (symbolic) links (<code>ln -s</code>). Creating a hard link to a file doesn’t copy (<code>cp</code>) the file itself, instead it creates a different filename pointing to the same i-node number and also increases the ‘link count’ of the file. This can be verified by running <code>ls -li</code> to see each file’s corresponding i-node number and link count.</p>

<p>Hard links can’t be made to directories, thereby preventing circular links. The book recounts how early UNIX implementations did allow this in order to facilitate directory creation. <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/mkdir.2.html"><code>mkdir</code></a> didn’t exist, so directories were created with <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/mknod.2.html"><code>mknod</code></a> and then links were made for <code>.</code> and <code>..</code> to facilitate directory traversal. It also reminds the reader that ‘links to directories’ are more or less possible with bind mounts.</p>

<h3 id="shared-pointers">Shared Pointers</h3>

<p>Hard links remind me of <a href="http://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/memory/shared_ptr"><code>shared_ptr</code></a> in C++11. I can imagine a scenario in which different processes need access to a common file but the common file needs to be deleted when all processes are finished with it. They can create a link to the file and use that to do their work, since it will be the same file as the original. When they are finished with the file, they can <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/unlink.2.html"><code>unlink</code></a> – remove the link – to the file. The file system will automatically delete the file itself when the number of links has reached zero. I don’t know if this is common – or even a correct – practice, nevertheless I immediately thought of this when I came across links.</p>

<h3 id="temporary-files">Temporary Files</h3>

<p>A trick in the spirit of the above is touched upon by the book. It talks about how a program might sometimes create a file, <code>unlink</code> it immediately, and then continue using the file knowing that the file will be destroyed 1) explicitly when the file descriptor is closed or 2) implicitly when the program closes. This is what <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man3/tmpfile.3.html"><code>tmpfile</code></a> does.</p>

<h2 id="symbolic-links">Symbolic Links</h2>

<p>Also known as soft links, these types of links are more commonly used by people. They simply consist of the <code>type</code> i-node field being set to <code>symlink</code> and the data blocks of the i-node set to the target path.</p>

<p>An interesting note discussed by the book is that some UNIX file systems (such as ext2, ext3, and ext4) perform an optimization where, if the target path can fit in the part of the i-node that would normally be used for data-block pointers, the path is simply stored there instead of externally. In the case of the author, the ext filesystems appropriate 60 bytes to the data-block pointers. Analysis of his system showed that of the 20,070 symbolic links, 97% were 60 bytes or smaller.</p>

<h2 id="directory-streams">Directory Streams</h2>

<p>Directory entries can be enumerated by getting a directory stream handle with <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man3/opendir.3.html"><code>opendir</code></a> (or <code>fdopendir</code> to avoid certain race conditions) and pulling directory entries <code>dirent</code> from the directory stream with <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/readdir.2.html"><code>readdir</code></a>.</p>

<p>Additionally, recursive file tree walking can be achieved using <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man3/ftw.3.html"><code>nftw</code></a> (new file tree walking) by passing it a callback to call on every entry.</p>

<h2 id="working-directories">Working Directories</h2>

<p>The working directory (<a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man3/getcwd.3.html"><code>getcwd</code></a>) of a process determines the reference point from which to resolve relative pathnames within the process. For example if the working directory is <code>/home/user</code> then a a file path of <code>../user2</code> will refer to <code>/home/user2</code>. Simple stuff. The working directory can be changed with <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/chdir.2.html"><code>chdir</code></a> and <code>fchdir</code>.</p>

<p>Aside from this, Linux (&gt; 2.6.16) provides various <code>*at()</code> calls, such as <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/openat.2.html"><code>openat</code></a>, which operate relative to a directory file descriptor. These calls (now part of SuSv4) help avoid certain race conditions and help facilitate an idea of “virtual working directories” which is particularly useful in multithreaded applications since every thread shares the working directory attribute of the process.</p>

<h2 id="root-directories">Root Directories</h2>

<p>Every process also has a root directory which serves as the reference point from which to resolve <em>absolute</em> pathnames (as opposed to relative pathnames with working directories). This is usually <code>/</code>, but can be changed with <a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/chroot.2.html"><code>chroot</code></a>, which is often used to create so called “chroot jails”, something FTP servers might do to limit a user’s filesystem exposure to their home directory.  One thing to remember to do is to change the working directory to the chrooted path, in effect “stepping into the jail.” Otherwise the user is able to continue roaming around outside the jail.</p>

<p>chroot jails aren’t a silver bullet. Some BSD derivatives provide a systemcall, <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi?query=jail&amp;apropos=0&amp;sektion=2&amp;manpath=FreeBSD+9.1-RELEASE&amp;arch=default&amp;format=html"><code>jail</code></a>, that handles various edge cases.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
